Inventory of the William X. Scheinman Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
William X. Scheinman Papers
1952-1999
98036
Scheinman, William X., 1927-
56 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 1 framed poster (26 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, reports, bulletins, serial issues, clippings, photographs, sound recordings, video tapes, and motion picture film, relating to American relations with Africa, the political and economic development of Kenya and other African countries, assistance to African students in the United States, and especially to the Kenyan political leader Tom Mboya. Includes correspondence with, writings by, and interviews of, Mboya.
Administrative Information
Access
Box 59 is closed. The remainder of the collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1998.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1927(?) Born
1940s Serves in U.S. Navy during World War II
1950s Founds Arnav Aircraft Associates, Inc.
1956 Meets Tom Mboya, Kenyan independence leader
1958-1961 Leading figure in the activities of the African-American Students Foundation, which brings African students to the United States and arranges for their college education
1960s-1990s Works as stock broker and investment adviser, publishing the newsletter, Timings
1970 Author, Why Most Investors Are Mostly Wrong Most of the Time
1999 May 24 Dies, Reno, Nevada
Scope and Content of Collection
Received at the Hoover Institution Archives in 1999, the William X. Scheinman papers consist primarily of correspondence and printed matter that reflect Scheinman's lifelong interest in African politics, particularly with respect to Kenya. Having met the Kenyan independence leader, Tom Mboya, in 1956, Scheinman was to identify himself with African causes, even while working as a businessman and investment adviser on Wall Street.
An important part of the collection consists of Scheinman's extensive correspondence with Tom Mboya. This exchange of letters, which was conducted from 1957 until Mboya's assassination in 1969, provides significant information concerning the Kenyan independence movement and its leading personalities, as well as documenting the first five years of the Kenyatta administration, in which Mboya served as Minister of Justice. In addition, the collection includes numerous speeches and writings by Mboya (see Tom Mboya File).
As one of the directors of the African-American Students Foundation, Scheinman was also involved in a program that enabled African students to attend American colleges and universities. Numerous records of this foundation are contained in the collection (see African-American Students Foundation File).
In addition, Scheinman collected extensive material about African countries besides Kenya (see Printed Matter and Subject File) and corresponded with some of the leading figures in the American civil rights movement (see Correspondence). The collection will be of most interest to African scholars, but it also reflects important aspects of modern American history, especially in the 1950s and 1960s.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Mboya, Tom.; African American Students Foundation.; American Committee on Africa.; Educational assistance, American--Africa.; Africa--Politics and government--1960-; Africa--Economic conditions--1960-; Kenya--Politics and government.; United States--Relations--Africa.; Africa--Relations--United States.; Video tapes.; Moving-pictures.; Phonorecords.; Phonotapes.
Collection Contents
- Biographical File, 1960-1963. (Folder : 1)
  Book dedication, brochures, invitations, programs, and souvenirs, and clippings and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Book dedication from Tom Mboya. Photocopy (Folder 1: 1)
  - Clippings, 1960 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Subject file - Trip in attendance of Kenyan independence celebrations, 1963 (Folder 1)
  - General. Includes brochures, commemorative stamps, and souvenirs (Folder 1: 3)
    - Invitations (Folder 1: 4)
    - Programs (Folder 1: 5)
- Correspondence, 1957-1999. (Folder : 1-2)
  Letters arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General (Folder 1)
    - A (Folder 1: 6)
    - B (Folder 1: 7)
    - C (Folder 1: 8)
    - D (Folder 1: 9)
    - E (Folder 1: 10)
    - F (Folder 1: 11)
    - G (Folder 1: 12)
    - H (Folder 1: 13)
    - J (Folder 1: 14)
    - K (Folder 1: 15)
    - L (Folder 1: 16)
    - M (Folder 1: 17)
    - N (Folder 1: 18)
    - O (Folder 1: 19)
    - P (Folder 1: 20)
    - R (Folder 1: 22)
    - S (Folder 2: 1)
    - T (Folder 2: 2)
    - U (Folder 2: 3)
    - V (Folder 2: 4)
    - W (Folder 2: 5)
    - Y (Folder 2: 6)
    - Z (Folder 2: 7)
  - Unidentified (Folder 2: 8)
  - Abernathy, Ralph, 1960 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Achieng, Aloys P., 1966-1985 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Africa Fund, 1984-1998 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Africa Watch, 1990 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Agency for the Performing Arts, Inc., 1963 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Akumu, James Dennis, 1960-1961 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Allen, John M., 1961 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Allimadi, E. Otema, 1967 (Folder 2: 16)
  - American Committee on Africa, 1958-1991. (Folder 2: 17)
    See also Houser, George M.
  - Angelou, Maya, 1994 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Ayodo, Samuel, 1960-1967 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Ball, John, 1962-1993 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Banda, H. Kamuzu, 1960 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Belafonte, Harry, 1963-1991 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Borden, Arthur M., 1966-1992 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Bowles, Chester, 1960-1961 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Brombart, David, 1966 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Brown, Irving, 1960-1966 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Burke, Fred, 1984 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Carson, Clayborne, 1998-1999 (Folder 2: 28)
  - Cartwright, Marguerite, 1961 (Folder 2: 29)
  - Chipembere, Henry B. M., 1965-1971 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Chiume, Jessie, 1984-1985 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Chiume, M. W. Kanyama (Folder 3)
    - 1959-1965 (Folder 3: 3)
    - 1981-1988 (Folder 3: 4)
    - 1991 (Folder 3: 5)
    - 1992-1998 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Coombs, Philip, 1961 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Diamond, Sara, 1997-1998 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Diggs, Charles C., Jr., 1959-1961 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Drake, St. Clair, 1960-1989 (Folder 4: 1)
  - Durst, Joseph, 1966 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Eban, Abba, 1986 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Edmonds, Douglas, 1961 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Fernandez, Arthur E., 1966 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Fisher, Christine, 1998 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Fissiha, Gebayanesh, 1960-1983 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Fodor, Napoleon, 1983-1984 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Fredericks, J. Wayne, 1961-1966 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Fulbright, J. William, 1960-1961 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Fung, Karen, 1993-1999 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Gabor, Robert, 1967-1998 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Galbraith, Nadine, 1998 (Folder 4: 13)
  - Gatheru, R. Mugo and family, 1959-1963 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Gichuru, James, 1960-1961 (Folder 4: 15)
  - Giesen Management, Inc., 1963 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Gill, Kuldip, 1966-1967 (Folder 4: 17)
  - Goldsworthy, David, 1989-1990 (Folder 4: 18)
  - Grant, Jack, 1961 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Grob, Stephen and Annette, 1967-1989 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Hagberg, Gordon, 1960-1966 (Folder 5: 3)
  - Harrington, Donald, 1960 (Folder 5: 4)
  - History Book Club, Inc., 1963 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Houser, George M., 1958-1998. (Folder 5: 6)
    See also American Committee on Africa
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1966-1975 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Institute of International Education, 1960 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Jack, Homer A., 1959-1983 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Jacobson, Jay, 1965-1969 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Jani, P. K., 1960-1961 (Folder 5: 11)
  - Kahn, Tom, 1960-1963 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Kaplan, Richard, 1961-1967 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Kaunda, Kenneth, 1960-1984 (Folder 5: 14)
  - Kennedy, Ethel, 1992 (Folder 5: 15)
  - Kennedy, Jacqueline, 1960 (Folder 5: 16)
  - Kennedy, Robert F., 1966 (Folder 5: 17)
  - Kheel, Theodore W., 1960 (Folder 5: 18)
  - King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1960-1966 (Folder 5: 19)
  - Kisaka, H. E. Mwambili, 1966 (Folder 5: 20)
  - Koinange, Mbiyu, 1960-1963 (Folder 5: 21)
  - Lewis, Anthony, 1994 (Folder 5: 22)
  - Little, Brown and Co., 1963 (Folder 5: 23)
  - Make, Vus, 1961 (Folder 5: 24)
  - Makeba, Miriam, 1962-1966 (Folder 5: 25)
  - Marshall, Thurgood, 1960-1967 (Folder 5: 26)
  - Mathenge, Joseph, 1960-1961 (Folder 5: 27)
  - Maxwell, John C., Jr., 1985-1986 (Folder 6: 1)
  - Closed Files moved to box 59 (Folder 6: 2-8)
  - Mboya, Tom (Folder 6)
    - 1957 (Folder 6: 9)
    - 1958 (Folder 6: 10)
    - 1959 (Folder 6: 11-12)
    - 1960 (Folder 7: 1-3)
    - 1961 (Folder 7: 4-5)
    - 1962 (Folder 7: 6)
    - 1963 (Folder 8: 1)
    - 1964-1965 (Folder 8: 2)
    - 1966 (Folder 8: 3-4)
    - 1967 (Folder 8: 5)
    - 1968 (Folder 8: 6)
    - 1969 (Folder 8: 7)
  - Mboya Okuku, Tom, 1984-1990 (Folder 9: 1)
  - Merrick, Mike, 1962 (Folder 9: 2)
  - Moi, Daniel T. Arap, 1961-1984 (Folder 9: 3)
  - Moikobu, Josephine, 1967-1998 (Folder 9: 4)
  - Montero, Frank, 1960-1993 (Folder 9: 5)
  - Morgan, Lee and Vicki, 1988 (Folder 9: 6)
  - Murra, John, 1960-1961 (Folder 9: 7)
  - Murumbi, Joseph and Sheila, 1960-1987 (Folder 9: 8)
  - Nabwera, H. E. Burudi, 1965-1989 (Folder 9: 9)
  - Ndiege, Odira and family, 1978-1990 (Folder 9: 10)
  - Ndiege, Peter P. Okong'o, 1960-1968 (Folder 9: 11)
  - New York Herald Tribune, 1963 (Folder 9: 12)
  - New York Mirror, 1961 (Folder 9: 13)
  - New York Times, 1958-1966 (Folder 9: 14)
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1960 (Folder 9: 15)
  - Njiri, Kariuki and Ruth, 1959-1977 (Folder 9: 16)
  - Nkomo, Joshua, 1960-1961 (Folder 9: 17)
  - Nundu, Otieno, 1969-1985 (Folder 9: 18)
  - Nyong'o, Isis, 1998 (Folder 9: 19)
  - Ochieng, Philip, 1988 (Folder 10: 1)
  - Ochieng Ochuonye, Willie, 1988-1989 (Folder 10: 2)
  - Odede, Simeon, 1960 (Folder 10: 3)
  - Odinga, Ajuma Oginga, 1960-1993 (Folder 10: 4)
  - Ojera, A. A., 1967 (Folder 10: 5)
  - Okuku, Alphonse, 1960-1969 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Operation Crossroads Africa, Inc., 1969 (Folder 10: 7)
  - Peck, James, 1966-1967 (Folder 10: 8)
  - Phelps-Stokes Fund, 1960-1975 (Folder 10: 9)
  - Rake, Alan, 1961 (Folder 10: 10)
  - Reid, Harry, 1989-1990 (Folder 10: 11)
  - Reuther, Victor G., 1961 (Folder 10: 12)
  - Roberto, Holden, 1960-1962 (Folder 10: 13)
  - Royce, Charles, 1991-1992 (Folder 10: 14)
  - Rustin, Bayard, 1960-1969 (Folder 10: 15)
  - Sagini, Lawrence G., 1984-1987 (Folder 10: 16)
  - Sanger, Clyde, 1963 (Folder 10: 17)
  - Saul, Hyman, 1967 (Folder 10: 18)
  - Savimbi, Jonas, 1962 (Folder 10: 19)
  - Scheinman, Robert, 1961-1966 (Folder 10: 20)
  - Scheinman, Sidney and Roslyn, 1961-1968 (Folder 10: 21)
  - Scheinman, William, Jr., 1998 (Folder 10: 22)
  - Shriver, Robert Sargent, Jr., 1960 (Folder 10: 23)
  - Sims, Albert, 1960-1961 (Folder 10: 24)
  - Smith, Mansfield, 1966 (Folder 10: 25)
  - Smythe, Hugh, 1966 (Folder 10: 26)
  - Sontheimer, Morton, 1966-1967 (Folder 10: 27)
  - Spivak, Lawrence, 1960-1969 (Folder 10: 28)
  - Springer-Kemp, Maida, 1960-1992 (Folder 10: 29)
  - Stephens, Robert F., 1987-1994 (Folder 10: 30)
  - Sutherland, Efua, 1961-1967 (Folder 11: 1)
  - Syracuse University, 1966-1967 (Folder 11: 2)
  - Thea, Stanley, 1966-1968 (Folder 11: 3)
  - Thompson, Frank, Jr., 1961 (Folder 11: 4)
  - Untermyer, Frank, 1960 (Folder 11: 5)
  - Von Auw, Ivan, 1959-1969 (Folder 11: 6)
  - Washington Post, 1993 (Folder 11: 7)
  - Weiss, Peter and Cora, 1960-1962 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Whitford, Richard L., 1967-1968 (Folder 11: 9)
- Correspondence, 1960-1995. (Folder 11-12)
  Articles, letter to the editor, notes, report, and speech for Tom Mboya, arranged chronologically by title
  - General - Notes (Folder 11)
    - 1960 (Folder 11: 10)
    - 1962 (Folder 11: 11)
    - 1963 (Folder 11: 12)
    - 1967 (Folder 11: 13)
    - 1980-1985 (Folder 11: 14)
    - 1993 (Folder 11: 15)
  - "Challenge of Development,", n.d. (Folder 11: 16)
    Typescript
  - Speech for Tom Mboya, n.d. (Folder 11: 17)
    Holograph and typescript
  - Letter to the editor, Sunday Post (Nairobi, Kenya), 1960 April 13. (Folder 11: 18)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Role of Tourism in Kenya's Developing Economy and a Program for Its Implementation,", 1966 July 31. (Folder 11)
    - Preliminary draft (Folder 11: 19-20)
    - Final draft, Chapters 1-16 (Folder 12: 1)
    - Final draft, Chapters 17-25 (Folder 12: 2)
  - "Racism at U.S. Embassy in Nairobi,", 1990 July 18. (Folder 12: 3)
  - "Whatever Happened to the African-American Dialogue?", 1995 July 4. (Folder 12: 4)
- Tom Mboya File, 1959-1983. (Folder 12)
  Address lists, articles, biographies, clippings, correspondence, eulogy, invitations, itineraries, printed matter, reports, and speeches, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Address lists of Kenyan government officials and others, 1963 (Folder 12: 5)
  - Articles and clippings about him, 1959-1983 (Folder 12: 6-8)
  - Articles and clippings (Contd.) (Folder 13: 1-6)
  - Articles and clippings (Contd.) (Folder 14: 1-6)
  - Biographical file, 1962-1982. (Folder 15: 1-3)
    Includes published biographies, eulogy, and genealogy. Typescript and printed copies
  - Speeches and writings, 1956-1969 (Folder 15)
    - Autobiographical statement, n.d. (Folder 15: 4)
    - "A Message to the People of Kenya,", n.d. (Folder 15: 5)
      Typescript, proofs, and printed copy
    - "My Observations on Recent Political Development,", n.d. (Folder 15: 6)
    - The Kenya Question: An African Answer, 1956 September. Printed copy (Folder 15: 7)
    - Kenya Faces the Future, 1959 (Folder 15: 8)
    - "Tom Mboya: An Autobiography," Africa Today, 1959 March-April. (Folder 15: 9)
      Printed copy
    - Interview, "Meet the Press," NBC, 1959 April 12. (Folder 15: 10)
    - Speech, Africa Freedom Day celebration, 1959 April 15. (Folder 15: 11)
    - "The New Africa - And American Responsibilities," ADA World, 1959 May. (Folder 16: 1)
    - "The Problems of Independence in Africa," speech, World Affairs Council of Northern California, Asilomar, California, 1959 May 2. (Folder 16: 2)
      Program and printed copy
    - Speech, International Ladies Garment Workers' Union convention, Miami Beach, Florida, 1959 May 14. (Folder 16: 3)
    - "Africa and the Great American Dream," speech, Howard University, Washington, D.C., 1959 June 5. (Folder 16: 4)
      Correspondence and typescript
    - "Key Questions for Awakening Africa," New York Times Magazine, 1959 June 28. (Folder 16: 5)
    - Letter to the editor, New York Times, 1959 November 8. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 16: 6)
    - Speech, Kenya Constitutional Conference, London, England, 1960 January 25. (Folder 16: 7)
    - "Observations on the Political Situation," New East African Standard, 1960 May 20. (Folder 16: 8)
    - Speech, Third All African Peoples' Conference, Cairo, Egypt, 1961 (Folder 16: 9)
    - Election speech, Nairobi, Kenya, 1961 February 25. (Folder 16: 10)
    - Open letter to Ian Macleod, 1961 April 1. (Folder 16: 11)
    - "Kenya's Political and Constitutional Deadlock,", 1961 April 13. (Folder 16: 12)
    - Speech, Africa Freedom Day celebration, 1961 April 17. (Folder 16: 13)
    - "Where Does KANU Stand?", 1961 May 1. (Folder 16: 14)
    - "African Higher Education: A Challenge to America," New Atlantic Monthly, 1961 July. (Folder 16: 15)
    - "Africanization of the Civil Service in Kenya,", 1961 October 28. (Folder 16: 16)
    - New Freedom and After, 1963 (Folder 16)
      - Typescript (Folder 16: 17)
      - Proofs (Folder 16: 18)
      - Corrections (Folder 17: 1)
      - Reviews (Folder 17: 2)
    - "Do White Men Have a Future in Africa?" New York Times Magazine, 1963 December 8. (Folder 17: 3)
    - "The 50-Year Struggle Which Has Its Climax in Independence," East African Standard, 1963 December 12. (Folder 17: 4)
    - "The Role of the Party in Independent Kenya," New Pan Africa, 1964 February 21. (Folder 17: 5)
    - "KANU Non-Alignment," New Africa Today, 1965 April. (Folder 17: 6)
    - "National Planning and the Government Budget,", 1966 (Folder 17: 7)
    - Interview, "Meet the Press," NBC, 1966 March 20. (Folder 17: 8)
      Correspondence and printed copy
    - "Realities and Visions," speech, Valparaiso University, Valparaiso, Indiana, 1966 March 23. (Folder 17: 9)
    - Speech concerning Kenyan development plan, 1966 May 5. (Folder 17: 10)
    - Speech concerning relations between Africa and the United States, 1966 August 15. (Folder 17: 11)
    - Speech, Economic Commission for Africa, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, 1967 January 16. (Folder 17: 12)
    - "An Escape from Stagnation," New Africa Report, 1967 March. (Folder 17: 13)
    - "Back to Africa Movement: An African Viewpoint,", 1969(?). (Folder 17: 14)
    - "Preparing for a General Election,", 1969 July. (Folder 17: 15)
    - Rebuttal to article in New Ebony, 1969 July 5. (Folder 17: 16)
    - "The American Negro Cannot Look to Africa for an Escape," New York Times Magazine, 1969 July 13. (Folder 17: 17)
  - Subject file, 1956-1969. (Folder 18)
    Correspondence, invitations, itineraries, printed matter, and reports
    - File closed, moved to box 59 (Folder 18: 1)
    - Films. Descriptions of footage depicting Tom Mboya (Folder 18: 2)
    - Radio and television appearances (Folder 18: 3)
    - Speaking engagements (Folder 18: 4-5)
    - Tom Mboya Memorial Fund (Folder 18: 6)
- African-American Students Foundation File, 1958-1963. (Folder 18-20)
  Bulletins, clippings, contracts, correspondence, forms, press releases, printed matter, records, and reports, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General, 1960-1961. (Folder 18: 7-8)
    Bulletins, forms, memoranda, and printed matter
  - Clippings, 1960-1961 (Folder 18: 9)
  - Contracts, 1960 (Folder 18: 10)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Folder 19: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Folder 19: 2-3)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Folder 19: 4-5)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Folder 19: 6)
  - Financial records, 1960-1961 (Folder 19: 7)
  - Press releases, 1960-1961 (Folder 19: 8)
  - Reports, 1960-1961 (Folder 20: 1)
  - Student records, 1960-1961 (Folder 20: 2)
- African-American Leadership Foundation File, 1989-1992. (Folder 20-21)
  Material relates to proposed film biography of Tom Mboya. Agreements, by-laws, certificate, correspondence, memoranda, proposals, and reports, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Agreements, by-laws, and certificate of incorporation, 1990 (Folder 20: 3)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Folder 20: 4)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Folder 20: 5)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Folder 20: 6)
  - Memoranda, 1989-1991 (Folder 20: 7)
  - Proposals, 1989 (Folder 20: 8)
  - Reports, 1991 (Folder 20: 9)
  - Tax records, 1990 (Folder 21: 1)
- Printed Matter, 1958-1999. (Folder 21-36)
  Articles, clippings, and serial issues, and other printed matter, largely relating to African politics, largely arranged chronologically
  - 1958 (Folder 21: 2-3)
  - 1959 (Folder 21: 4-7)
  - 1959 (Contd.) (Folder 22: 1-2)
  - 1960 (Folder 22: 3-5)
  - 1960 (Contd.) (Folder 23-24)
  - 1960 (Contd.) (Folder 25: 1-2)
  - 1961 (Folder 25: 3-6)
  - 1962 (Folder 26: 1-3)
  - 1963 (Folder 26: 4-6)
  - 1963 (Contd.) (Folder 27: 1)
  - 1964 (Folder 27: 2-7)
  - 1964 (Contd.) (Folder 28: 1-3)
  - 1965 (Folder 28: 4-7)
  - 1965 (Contd.) (Folder 29: 1-3)
  - 1966 (Folder 29: 4-7)
  - 1966 (Contd.) (Folder 30: 1-6)
  - 1967 (Folder 31: 2-6)
  - 1968 (Folder 31: 3)
  - 1969 (Folder 31: 4-5)
  - 1970 (Folder 31: 6)
  - 1971 (Folder 31: 7)
  - 1982 (Folder 31: 8)
  - 1983 (Folder 31: 9-10)
  - 1984 (Folder 32: 1-6)
  - 1985 (Folder 32: 7)
  - 1985 (Contd.) (Folder 33: 1)
  - 1986 (Folder 33: 2)
  - 1987 (Folder 33: 3-4)
  - 1988 (Folder 33: 5-6)
  - 1989 (Folder 33: 7-8)
  - 1990 (Folder 34: 1-2)
  - 1991 (Folder 34: 3-4)
  - 1992 (Folder 34: 5)
  - 1993 (Folder 34: 6)
  - 1993 (Contd.) (Folder 35: 1)
  - 1994 (Folder 35: 2-4)
  - 1995 (Folder 35: 5-6)
  - 1996 (Folder 35: 7)
  - 1997 (Folder 36: 1)
  - 1998 (Folder 36: 2)
  - 1999 (Folder 36: 3-4)
- Subject File, 1958-1999. (Folder 36-48)
  Articles, correspondence, programs, reports, serial issues, statistics, thesis, and clippings and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Africa Fund (Folder 36: 5)
  - African Explorations Limited (Folder 36: 6)
  - Agar, Omolo (Folder 36: 7)
  - All-African People's Conference, Accra, Ghana, 1958 (Folder 36: 8-10)
  - American Committee on Africa (Folder 36: 11)
  - American Committee on Africa (Contd.) (Folder 37: 1-5)
  - Amistead Research Center (Folder 37: 6)
  - Angola - Politics and government (Folder 38: 1)
  - Chiume, Kanyama (Folder 38: 2)
  - Council for Educational Cooperation with Africa (Folder 38: 3-6)
  - Drake, St. Clair (Folder 38: 7)
  - East African student airlifts, 1959-1961. (Folder 39: 1-5)
    Includes doctoral thesis by Mansfield Irving Smith
  - Institute of International Education (Folder 40: 1)
  - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (Folder 40: 2)
  - Investments (Folder 40: 3-6)
  - Kenya (Folder 41)
    - Economic conditions (Folder 41: 1-4)
    - Foreign relations (Folder 41: 5)
    - Politics and government (Folder 41: 6)
    - Politics and government (Contd.) (Folder 42: 1-5)
    - Politics and government (Contd.) (Folder 43-46)
  - King, Martin Luther, Jr. (Folder 47: 1)
  - Malawi - Politics and government (Folder 47: 2-3)
  - Marshall, Thurgood (Folder 47: 4)
  - Mboyo, Alakie (Folder 47: 5)
  - Operation Crossroads Africa (Folder 47: 6)
  - Ouko, Robert (Folder 47: 7)
  - Phelps-Stokes Fund (Folder 47: 8-9)
  - Rustin, Bayard (Folder 48: 1)
  - Tourism (Folder 48: 2-5)
- Photographs, 1960-1963. (Folder 49-50)
  14 envelopes of photographs depicting William Scheinman and his family, John F. Kennedy, Tom Mboya, Alphonse Okuku, East African student airlift, Kenya constitutional conference, and Kenyan independence celebrations
  - William Scheinman and family. Includes print with Hubert H. Humphrey (Folder 49: 1-2)
  - John F. Kennedy with African students (Folder 49: 3)
  - Tom Mboya (Folder 49: 4-5)
  - Alphonse Okuku (Folder 49: 6)
  - East African student airlift, 1959 (Folder 49: 7-12)
    Includes negatives
  - Kenya constitutional conference, London, England, 1960 (Folder 49: 13)
  - Kenyan independence celebrations, 1963 (Folder 49: 14)
  - Unidentified (Folder 50: 1-2)
- Slides. Two boxes of transparencies depicting William Scheinman, his family, and various other individuals (Folder 50: 3-4)
- Video Tapes, 1959 (Folder 51)
  - Interview of Tom Mboya conducted by Bishop James Pike, 1959 (Folder 51: 1)
  - "Stop the Violence," documentary on South Africa, n.d. (Folder 51: 2)
- Audio Tapes, 1959-1966. (Folder 51)
  25 phonotape cassettes and 19 phonotapes of interviews with and speeches by Tom Mboya, Kenneth Kaunda, Kwame Nkrumah, and Julius Nyerere
  - Phonotape cassettes (Folder 51)
    - Tom Mboya, 1959-1965. (Folder 51: 3-27)
      Includes interviews and speeches
    - Kenneth Kaunda, 1966 (Folder 51: 28)
    - Kwame Nkrumah, 1961 (Folder 51: 29)
    - Julius Nyerere, 1961 (Folder 51: 30)
  - Phonotapes. 18 recordings of speeches by Tom Mboya, 1959, and 1 recording (box 55) of gospel music (Folder 52-55)